the surface area of a sphere is 4 pi
times its radius squared exactly four
times the area of a circle with the same
radius but why Archimedes had a very
beautiful proof that this surface area
is the same as the area of a cylinder
that encloses that sphere if you
disregard the circular caps of that
cylinder the idea is that if you shine
some light from the z-axis perpendicular
to that axis then if you compare the
area of a small rectangle drawn on that
sphere to the area of the shadow cast on
that cylinder those two areas turn out
to be the same this isn't obvious but
when you work it out that shadow is a
copy of the original Little rectangle
but squished down in One Direction and
stretched out in another when you
analyze the relevant geometry the two
effects actually cancel out perfectly
treating the sphere as a sum of all of
these little patches and the cylinder as
a sum of all of those Shadows we can
infer that the surface area of the
sphere is the same as the area of that
cylinder now the cylinder is something
you can unwrap into a rectangle where
one side length corresponds to the
circum